<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on UoP Bioinformatics Group</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on UoP Bioinformatics Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Sam Robson</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/project/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Changes in microbial communities of Cliona celeta during observed changes in sponge health</title>
      <link>/project/2017-09-29_microbial_community_of_cliona_celeta_during_observed_changes_in_sponge_health/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/2017-09-29_microbial_community_of_cliona_celeta_during_observed_changes_in_sponge_health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cliona celeta is a yellow boring sponge found around the waters of the UK. The diversity of sponges in the Skomer Marine Nature Reserve has been surveyed since the 1990s. In 2013 divers observed apparent disease in C. celeta individuals across Skomer Island and the Marloes Peninsula. The previously healthy yellow sponge became colonised by fouling organisms followed by tissue decay and patches of black necrotic sponge. This issue appears to be seasonal, largely seen between the months of March and October, and is the first recorded incidence of sponge disease in temperate coastal waters. In addition, several sponges were seen to be fouled by algal and invertebrate species, without progression to the black state, which is indicative of reduced anti-fouling mechanisms in the sponge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-biological-sciences/staff/dr-joanne-preston.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr Joanne Preston&lt;/a&gt;, we are working to identify the change in microbial communities following the shift between healthy and fouled or necrotic tissue in sponges based on microbiological culturing and 16S rDNA sequencing of the sponge host and the microbial communities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genotyping of Ancient DNA from Crew Members from the Mary Rose</title>
      <link>/project/2017-09-29_genotyping_of_crew_members_of_the_mary_rose/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/2017-09-29_genotyping_of_crew_members_of_the_mary_rose/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Built in Portsmouth in 1510, the Mary Rose was the flagship of the fleet of Henry VIII, and had a long and lustrious career until it capsized north of the Isle of Wight in the Battle of the Solent in 1545. Fewer than 35 of the roughly 400 crew members escaped. The wreck was discovered in 1971, and following years of excavation activities the hull was raised from the seabed in 1982 and transported to its home port of Portsmouth. Since then, years of archaeological work has been carried out on the hull itself and on the nearly 20,000 artefacts that have so far been discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-biological-sciences/staff/dr-garry-scarlett.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr Garry Scarlett&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Portsmouth, and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.maryrose.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mary Rose Museum&lt;/a&gt;, we will be looking to understand more about the members of the crew by working on genotyping of the ancient DNA from the skeletons of crew members raised from the wreckage. Using whole genome sequencing techniques, we hope to develop an understanding of phenotypic characteristics, disease traits and geographic information of crew members of one of the most famous ship wrecks in history.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development of Bioinformatics Tools</title>
      <link>/project/2017-08-17_development-of-bioinformatics-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/2017-08-17_development-of-bioinformatics-tools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As well as collaborating with researchers from throughout the School of Pharmacy and Biomedical Sciences, we are also working to develop several tools that we have developed to release these for use by the wider bioinformatics community. These tools will be made available via the University of Portsmouth &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/uopbioinformatics&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; account, as well as directly from the University of Portsmouth &lt;a href=&#34;../../software/index.html&#34;&gt;Bioinformatics Group website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Anti-Fouling Coatings on Marine Biofilms</title>
      <link>/project/2017-08-17_anti-fouling-marine-biofilms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/2017-08-17_anti-fouling-marine-biofilms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Marine biofilms, or &amp;ldquo;biofouling&amp;rdquo;, are communities of micro-organisms bound together on a surface by an extracellular matrix composed of extracellular polymeric substances (EPS). Biofilms consist predominantly of phytoplankton (particularly diatoms which are photosynthesising algae) and bacteria, which bind to surfaces in the marine environment to form complex 3 dimensional surface structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formation of these biofilms can affect all types of surfaces in the marine environment, and substrates include such man-made structures as the hulls of ships, nets used by fishing trawlers, pipelines used to transport oil and gas, and boat propellors. Biofilm formation on ships can have a costly impact due to increased drag - for example the increased cost of fuel has been estimated at around $56 million per year for DDG-51 naval ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this reason, testing novel antifouling substrates that are environmentally benign is of great importance to many marine-based industries. Working together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-biological-sciences/staff/maria-salta.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Maria Salta&lt;/a&gt; we have been analysing the changes in bacterial communities on different man-made surfaces using next-generation sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Radiation Exposure in the Environment</title>
      <link>/project/2017-08-17_effect-of-radiation-exposure-on-fish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/2017-08-17_effect-of-radiation-exposure-on-fish/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exposure to radiation can have deleterious effects on gene expression regulation, particularly due to increased DNA damage and deregulation of DNA damage checkpoint pathways. Working together with Dr. Adelaide Lerebours, we are performing differential expression analyses to understand the effects of radiation on 3-spined stickleback under laboratory conditions, and in particular attempting to characterise the differences between normal and abnormal offspring of exposed parents to understand how mutations are passed down through the lineage. In addition, we are looking at the effects of radiation exposure in the field, by looking at the effects of radiation exposure on lakes around the Chernobyl nuclear power station which suffered a catastrophic meltdown in 1986. The effects of this are still being felt today, and this project will allow us to understand the negative impact that this disaster has had on aquatic life in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gene Expression Profiling of Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy</title>
      <link>/project/2017-08-17_expression-profiling-of-dmd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/2017-08-17_expression-profiling-of-dmd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Duchenne muscular dystrophy (DMD) is an X-linked recessive form of muscular dystrophy typically presenting in boys at around the age of four. DMD is caused by mutations in the DMD gene, which is the largest gene in the genome with 79 exons encoding a range of dystrophin proteins. These proteins are expressed in skeletal and cardiac muscles and also in brain and other non-muscle tissues, where they have specific roles. Their absence due to DMD mutations causes specific abnormalities such as progressive muscle weakness and wasting and cognitive deficits. Muscle weakness begins in the upper legs and pelvis but quickly spreads until boys are unable to walk and eventually cannot breathe unaided.  As yet, no cure exists for DMD, despite it being the most common form of muscular dystrophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-pharmacy-and-biomedical-sciences/staff/prof-darek-gorecki.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Professor Darek Gorecki&lt;/a&gt;, we are using RNA seq analysis to identify the changes in expression associated with a point mutation in the Dmd gene in a dystrophic mouse model. By identifying the pathways most impacted by the dystrophic phenotype, we hope to identify novel areas for future therapeutic intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Role of Variant Histones in Xenopus Development</title>
      <link>/project/2017-08-17_role-of-variant-histones-on-xenopus-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/2017-08-17_role-of-variant-histones-on-xenopus-development/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The variant histones H2A.Z1 and H2A.Z2 are distinct but highly homologous genes. As yet, functional differences between these two variants have not been elucidated. However, recent work by researchers at the university of Portsmouth have identified distinct roles for these two proteins in early development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-biological-sciences/staff/prof-matt-guille.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Professor Matt Guille&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-biological-sciences/staff/dr-fiona-myers.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Fiona Myers&lt;/a&gt;, we are examining the differential role of these highly similar but distinct proteins during the development of Xenopus laevis at the transcriptional level.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcriptome Profiling Of The Radula of Patella vulgata</title>
      <link>/project/2017-08-17_transcriptome-profiling-of-common-limpet/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/2017-08-17_transcriptome-profiling-of-common-limpet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The radula is a long chitinous ribbon-like proboscus containing many tiny teeth that is used by almost all molluscs for feeding. The radula is scraped across the surface to which the mollusc is attached to isolate food before it enters the esophagus. The teeth, or denticles, of the radula in the common limpet (&lt;em&gt;Patella vulgata&lt;/em&gt;) have been shown to have the highest tensile strength of any naturally occuring material, outperforming even the high strength of spider silk (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4387522/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Barber &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt; (2015)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working together with researchers at the University of Portsmouth including &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-engineering/staff/professor-asa-barber.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Professor Asa Barber&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-pharmacy-and-biomedical-sciences/staff/prof-darek-gorecki.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Professor Darek Gorecki&lt;/a&gt;, we are performing transcriptional profiling throughout the development of the radula to understand the gene pathways involved in the natural generation of this incredibly strong biomaterial.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
